Elisabeth Tooker Papers 1945-1994 Mss.Ms.Coll.84
American Philosophical Society
Elisabeth Tooker Papers
1945-1994
Mss.Ms.Coll.84
American Philosophical Society
42.0 Linear feet
An anthropologist and student of Native American cultures, Elisabeth Tooker devoted a long career, much of it as a professor at Temple University, to study of the culture and ethnohistory of the Iroquois Indians of New York State. The Tooker Papers is arranged in six series, and contain her correspondence, subject files, research notes, and both published and unpublished papers.
Tooker, Elisabeth, 1927-
Separated Materials note
Photographs have been removed from Series I-V and placed in Series VI. Cross references appear in the original series. Reprints have been moved to the printed materials collection of the APS library. If a reprint was found as an enclosure, a photocopy of the title page was filed in its place. To retrieve reprints, consult the card catalog for printed materials.
Also removed from the collection were seven sound tape reels: "The Seneca Language"; "Indians: Semu Huaute, Medicine Man"; and "Nation within a Nation" (the latter is comprised of five reels). To retrieve these items, consult the card catalog for manuscript materials.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Tooker Papers were donated by Elisabeth Tooker in 1994.
Scope and Contents note
The Elisabeth Tooker Papers (1945-1994) contain correspondence, subject files, manuscripts of published and unpublished works by Tooker, manuscripts by colleagues, field notes by Tooker, and photographs, which document Tooker's career as an anthropologist. The bulk of the collection covers the 1960s to the 1980s.
The papers (12 boxes; 5.75 linear feet) are divided into six series:
Series I Correspondence: 1949-1994 (6 boxes; 2.75 linear feet)
Series II Subject Files: 1945-1993 (3 boxes;.75 linear feet)
Series III Works by Tooker: 1949-1993 (2 boxes; 1 linear foot)
Series IV Works by Others: 1969-1989 (1 box; 6 folders)
Series V Field Notes: 1950-1982 (3 boxes; 1.25 linear feet)
Series VI Photographs: 1951-1973 (1 box; 4 folders)
Biographical/Historical note
An anthropologist and Iroquoian scholar, Elisabeth Jane Tooker was born on August 2, 1927 in Brooklyn, New York. Following an undergraduate career at Radcliffe College, from which she graduated in 1949, Tooker pursued graduate study in anthropology at the University of Arizona (MA, 1953), and Radcliffe, working on Indians of the American Southwest.
Before completing her degree at Radcliffe, Tooker was employed as a Teaching Fellow at Harvard from 1956-1957, and in 1957, she accepted a position as Instructor at the State University of New York at Buffalo. Tooker remained at SUNY Buffalo for two years after completion of her dissertation, "Ritual, Power and the Supernatural: A Comparative Study of Indian Religions in Southwestern United States," in March, 1958, before joining the faculty at Mount Holyoke College as Assistant Professor. A grant from the National Institute of General Medical Science (part of the National Institutes of Health) in 1964 enabled her to spend an intensive year in Cambridge, Mass., studying North American Indian curing practices and theories of disease.
Shortly after returning from her leave in 1965, Tooker accepted a position at Temple University, where she remained for the rest of her career, earning promotion to Associate Professor in 1967 and Professor in 1977. During her stay at Temple, she continued her research through a Temple Summer Faculty Research Award and Research Grant-in-Aid in 1966, a Study Leave for the academic year 1971-1972, a fellowship from the National Endowment for the Humanities (1981-1982), and a Smithsonian Institution Post-Doctoral Fellowship (1989-1990). She was also a Visting Professor at the State University of New York at Albany 1978-1979.
From the time of her move to Philadelphia, Tooker began increasingly to concentrate her research on the history and culture of Indians in the Northeast, and particularly the Iroquois. Among her several books are An ethnography of the Huron Indians, 1615-1649 (1964); The Indians of the Northeast: a critical bibliography (1978), and Lewis H. Morgan on Iroquois Material Culture (1994), along with several edited volumes, including four volumes of the proceedings of the American Ethnological Society (1978-1981), one volume from the Conference on Iroquois Research (1965), and three volumes of An Iroquois Sourcebook. Tooker was also a contributing author and a member of the planning committee of the Northeast volume of the Handbook of North American Indians that was published in 1978.
Tooker has been a member of many professional anthropological organizations, including the American Ethnological Society (editor of American Ethnologist, 1978-1982); the American Society for Ethnohistory (Executive Committee, 1973-1975; President, 1981-1982); the Conference on Iroquois Research (Planning Committee; Program Chair); the Northeastern Anthropological Association (Secretary, 1966-1968); and the Philadelphia Anthropological Society (Vice-President, 1967; President, 1969; Treasurer, 1988-1992). Her success in the profession has earned recognition as a Fellow of the American Association for the Advancement of Science (1960), as an alumna member of Phi Beta Kappa (through Radcliffe College, 1974), and as recipient of the Cornplanter Medal for Iroquois Research (1986).
In other professional activities, Tooker has served as a consultant to the exhibit, "American Indian Life, 1776-1976," at the University Museum of the University of Pennsylvania (for which she co-authored an exhibit catalog); a member of the Visiting Committee of the Board of Overseers of Harvard University to the Peabody Museum of Archaeology and Ethnology (1977-1981); a member of the Phillips Fund grant committee of the American Philosophical Society (1979); a member of the National Advisory Committee of the Conference on Native American Studies at Oklahoma State University (1982-1985); and a Consulting Scholar for the University of Pennsylvania's University Museum of Archaeology and Anthropology (1982-present). Tooker became Professor Emerita at Temple University in 1992, and she currently resides in Philadelphia.
Abler, Thomas F.; Barbeau, Marius, 1883-1969; Chafe, Wallace L.; Darnell, Regna; Day, Gordon M.; Deardorff, Merle H., d.1971; Einhorn, Arthur; Fenton, William N., (William Nelson), 1908-2005; Jennings, Francis P.; Lex, Barbara W.; Mohawk nation at Akwesasne.; Rothenberg, Diane; Snow, Dean R.; Stocking, George W., 1928-; Sturtevant, William C.; Trigger, Bruce Graham; Anthropologists.; Cayuga Indians; Clippings.; Digital images; Eastern Woodlands Indians; Gelatin silver prints; Handbook of North American Indians; Handsome Lake Religion; Indians of North America--Arizona; Indians of North America--New York (State); Iroquois Indians; Kinzua Dam (N.Y.); Maps.; Mohawk Indians; Negatives; Oneida Indians; Onondaga Indians; Papago Indians; Photographs; Photomechanical prints; Picture-writing; Postcards; Seneca Indians; Seneca Indians--Religion; Slides.; Southwest Indians; Tohono O'Odham Indians; Tuscarora Indians; Women anthropologists; Wyandot Indians; Yaqui Indians
- Series I. Correspondence, 1949-1994
  Scope and Contents note
  Incoming and outgoing typescript letters, carbons, and postcards generated during Tooker's career. Series I is arranged alphabetically by correspondent's name and then chronologically within each folder.
  When a correspondence file includes letters to a third party (i.e., not Tooker), the name is indented on the container list under the file name.
  Unidentified correspondence has been filed as "Unidentified" and is arranged chronologically. Enclosed manuscripts have been removed from this series and placed in Series III or IV as appropriate. As with the reprints, a photocopy of the title page was filed with the original letter. Letters of reference are filed under the name of the person who is the subject of the letter.
  Correspondents include anthropologists, government officials, students, publishers, Native Americans, and interested amateur anthropologists. Among the topics covered in this series are: ethnology, ethnohistory, religion, and social organization of Iroquois, Papago, and Yaqui Indians; and Iroquois political organization.
  There is correspondence concerning Tooker's work on the Northeast volume of the Handbook of North American Indians, both as a contributor and as a member of the planning committee; her work as a member of the Visiting Committee of the Board of Overseers of Harvard College to the Peabody Museum of Archaeology and Ethnology from 1977 to 1981; and her work as Secretary of the Northeastern Anthropological Association from 1966 to 1968. Correspondence concerning the Conference on Iroquois Research is filed in Series II.
  - A - De (Box 1)
    - Abler, Thomas F., 1966-1993
      -See also Ser.I, Bieder, Robert E.
      -See also Ser.I, Handbook of North American Indians
      -See also Ser.I, Weaver, Sally M.
    - Abrams, George Henry, 1965-1983
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1960
    - American Philosophical Society, 1968
    - Axtell, James, 1987
    - Bahr, Donald, 1977-1989
    - Bailey, Edna, 1967-1968
    - Bailey, Garrick Alan, 1986
    - Bannerman, Robin M.
      -See Ser.I, Fenton, William N.
    - Barbeau, C. Marius, 1964-1967
    - Barber, Carroll, 1950
    - Barbour, Philip L., 1968, 1970
    - Barnes, R.H., 1991
    - Becker, Marshall Joseph, 1973-1993
    - Becker, Mary A. Druke, 1985-1986
      -See also Ser.I, Hamell, George R.
    - Bieder, Robert E., 1980
      - Abler, Thomas S.
        -See also Ser.I, The Newberry Library Center for the History of the American Indian
    - Bierhorst, John, 1991
    - Bilharz, Joy, 1985-1991
    - Bishop, Charles, 1979, 1981
    - Blau, Harold, 1964-1969
      -See also Ser.I, Fenton, William N.
    - Bradley, James W., 1976-1989
    - Browman, David L., 1977
    - Buchler, Ira R.
      -See Ser.I, Selby, Henry A.
    - Campisi, Jack, 1971-1981
    - Carnes, Mark, 1987
    - Carney, Sidney
    - Ceci, Lynn, 1968-1989
      -See also Ser.I, Dincauze, Dena F.
    - Chafe, Wallace L., 1959-1992
      - Mithun, Marianne
        -See also Ser.I, Foster, Michael K.
        -See also Ser.I, White, Marian E.
        -See also Ser.II, Conference on Iroquois Research
    - Chamberlain, Dwight Lewis, 1979
    - Cherokee-Iroquois Conference, 1978
    - Christie, T. Laird, 1982-1983
    - Clifton, James A., 1977-1991
    - Congdon, Charles E., 1968
      - Fenton, William N.
    - Cook, Bill, 1987
    - Crozier, Dan
      -See Ser.I, Deardorff, Merle H.
    - Currier, Margaret, 1974
      -See also Ser.I, Harvard University.
      Peabody Museum of Archaeology and Ethnology
    - Darnell, Regna, 1968-1992
    - Davenport, William, 1968-1979
    - Day, Gordon M., 1965-1985
    - Deardorff, Mary, n.d.
    - Deardorff, Merle H., 1964-1971
      - Crozier, Dan
      - Fenton, William N.
  - Di - G (Box 2)
    - Dincauze, Dena F., 1990
    - Dobyns, Henry F., 1958-1989
    - Drooker, Penelope B., 1990
    - Druke, Mary A.
      -See Ser.I, Becker, Mary A. Druke
    - Eggan, Fred, 1978-1982
    - Egloff, Nancy D., 1988-1989
    - Einhorn, Arthur, 1962-1990
    - Encyclopedia Britannica, 1971-1972
    - Evaneshko, Veronica, 1972-1974, n.d.
    - Fanning, Ralph, 1959-1970
    - Fenton, William Nelson
      - Bannerman, Robin M., 1966
      - Blau, Harold, 1969
      - Carney, Sidney, 1965
      - Deardorff, Merle H., 1968
      - Foley, Denis P., 1975
      - Hertzberg, Hazel W., 1976
      - Hudson, Charles, 1977
      - Sturtevant, William C., 1976-1977
      - Torok, Charles H., 1968
      - White, Marian E., 1959
        -See also Ser.I, Congdon, Charles E.
        -See also Ser.I, Deardorff, Merle H.
        -See also Ser.II, Iroquoia
        - Folder 1, 1958-1965
        - Folder 2, 1966-1968
        - Folder 3, 1969-1975
        - Folder 4, 1976-1985
        - Folder 5, 1986-1994
    - Fischer, John L., 1964
    - Fogelson, Raymond D., 1964-1990
    - Foley, Denis P.
    - Foster, Michael K., 1969-1991
      - Chafe, Wallace L., 1987
      - Mithun, Marianne, 1987
      - Snow, Dean R., 1988, 1991
    - Fowler, Don D., 1972, 1987
    - Francillon, Mark, 1989
    - Frisch, Jack A., 1976
      - Handbook of North American Indians
    - Gehring, Charles
      -See Ser.I, Starna, William A.
    - Gifford, Carol A., 1965-1989
      - Gifford, James C.
    - Gifford, James C., 1964-1965, 1973
      -See also Ser.I, Gifford, Carol A.
      -See also Ser.I, Tuck, James A.
    - Greaves, Thomas C., 1978-1980
    - Griffin, James B.
    - Grinde, Donald A., Jr., 1989, 1993
      -See also Ser.I, Johansen, Bruce
    - Gruber, Jacob W., 1970, 1987
      -See also Ser.I, Northeastern Anthropological Association
      -See also Ser.I, Temple University
  - Ha - Hu (Box 3)
    - Hagedorn, Nancy L., 1988
    - Hale, Thomas, 1982
    - Hall, Robert L.
      -See Ser.I, Hamell, George R.
    - Hamell, George R., 1976-1988
      - Becker, Mary A. Druke
      - Fenton, William N.
      - Hall, Robert L.
      - Mithun, Marianne
    - Hamilton College, 1963-1970
    - Handbook of North American Indians
      - Abler, Thomas S., 1977
      - Campisi, Jack, 1974, 1976
      - Eggan, Fred, 1974
      - Fenton, William N., 1971, 1974-1976
      - Griffin, James B., 1974
      - Sturtevant, William C.
      - Trigger, Bruce G.
      - Wallace, Anthony F.C., 1971-1972
        -See also Ser.I, Frisch, Jack A.
        -See also Ser.I, Landy, David
        -See also Ser.I, Torok, Charles H.
        -See also Ser.II, Handbook of North American Indians
        - Folder 1, 1970-1973
        - Folder 2, 1974-1975
        - Folder 3, Jan.-Jun. 1976
        - Folder 4, Jul. 1976-1979
    - Harvard University, 1957-1977
      -See also Ser.I, Radcliffe College
    - Harvard University. Peabody Museum ofArchaeology and Ethnology
      - Currier, Margaret
        -See also Ser.II, same title
        - Folder 1, 1966-Sep. 1980
        - Folder 2, Oct. 1980-1981
    - Hauptman, Laurence M., 1988-1993
    - Haury, Emil W., 1954
    - Hayes, Jack, 1971
    - Hershey Museum of American Life, 1984
    - Hertzberg, Hazel W., 1962-1988
    - Hohenberg, John, 1964, 1977-178
    - Howard, James H., 1972
    - Hudson, Charles
    - Human Relations Area Files, Inc., 1983-1988
      - Martin, Marlene
    - The Huntington, 1975-1983
    - Huronia Historical Development Council, 1967, 1969
      -See also Ser.I, Sainte-Marie Among the Hurons
  - J - Ri (Box 4)
    - Jennings, Francis P., 1984-1993
    - Johansen, Bruce, 1993
    - Judkins, Russell A., 1986-1987
    - Katz, Stanley N., 1983, 1988
    - Kelly, William H., 1949
    - Klein, Alexander, 1972
    - Kluckhohn, Clyde, 1958-1960
    - Kolb, Charles C., 1983
    - Kolb, Joy
      -See Ser.I, Bilharz, Joy
    - Landy, David, 1977
      - Handbook of North American Indians
    - Laughlin, William S., 1990
    - Lessard, Rosemary, 1971
    - Lex, Barbara W., 1966-1974
    - Libby, Dorothy, 1961-1967
    - Lounsbury, Floyd G., 1958-1991
    - Lurie, Alison, 1975
    - McCall, Daniel F., 1977, 1982
    - McFeat, Tom F.S., 1961-1969
    - McGill-Queens University Press, 1973
    - Martin, Marlene
      -See Ser.I, Human Relations Area Files, Inc.
    - Mason, Carol, 1964, 1969
    - Maybury-Lewis, David, 1967
    - Mithun, Marianne
      -See Ser.I, Chafe, Wallace L.
      -See Ser.I, Foster, Michael K.
    - Mosteller, Frederick, 1957, 1964, n.d.
    - Museum of Northern Arizona, 1975-1977
    - Myers, Merlin G., 1977
    - Namias, June, 1987-1993
    - National Research Council, 1985
    - New York State Museum, 1969
    - The Newberry Library Center for theHistory of the American Indian, 1975-1978
      - Bieder, Robert E.
      - Jennings, Francis P.
    - Northeastern Anthropological Association, 1966-1968
      - Gruber, Jacob W.
      - Opler, Marvin K.
      - Roberts, John M.
      - Trigger, Bruce G.
    - Officer, James E., 1967-1968
      -See also Ser.I, United States.
      - Department of the Interior. Bureau of Indian Affairs
    - Oklahoma State University, 1982-1985
    - Ontario Archaeology, 1985
    - Opler, Marvin K., 1959
    - Osgood, Cornelius, 1962, 1965
    - Parker, Judith, 1968
    - Pendergast, James F., 1965-1993
    - Pennsylvania Archaeologist, 1991
    - Pia, J. Joseph, 1966-1980
    - Plant, Christopher H., 1876-1983
    - Pollak, Janet Sue, 1970-1976
    - Pratt, Peter P., 1966-1968
    - Preston, Richard J., 1968-1976
    - Prisch, Betty C., 1985
    - Radcliffe College, 1954-1975
    - Raitt, Thomas M., 1978
    - Rajnovich, Grace, 1990
    - Rapoport, Robert, 1958
      - Vogt, Evon Z.
    - Reader's Digest, 1976-1977
    - Richards, Cara E., 1965-1971
    - Richter, Daniel K., 1988, 1990
    - Ridley, Frank, 1964
  - Ro - T (Box 5)
    - Roberts, John M., 1956-1986
    - Robie, Harry, 1982-1992
    - Rochester Museum and Science Center
    - Rose, Richard, 1987
    - Rothenberg, Diane, 1977, 1986-1987
    - Russell, Eber L., 1965
      - Taylor, Peggy
      - Taylor, Walter
    - Sainte-Marie Among the Hurons, 1970-1977, n.d.
    - Schwarz, John E., 1981
    - Schweitzer, Marjorie M. Gardner, 1982
    - Science, 1974
      -See also Ser.I, Wiren, Harold N.
    - Selby, Henry A., 1968
      - Buchler, Ira R.
    - Sempowski, Martha L., 1985
    - Settee, Priscilla, 1972
    - Shimony, Annemarie, 1961-1992
    - Shoemaker, Nancy, 1988
    - Simmons, William S., 1978
    - Smith, Kidd, 1965
    - Smithsonian Institution, 1962-1972
      - Sturtevant, William C.
    - Snow, Dean R., 1983-1991
    - Southwestern Journal of Anthropology, 1959-1967
    - Speck, Frank G. (Mrs.), 1959
    - Starna, William A., 1982, 1987-1988
      - Gehring, Charles
    - The State Historical Society of Wisconsin, 1965
    - State University of New York at Buffalo, 1957-1960
    - Steckley, John, 1983
      -See also Ser.I, Ontario Archaeology
    - Stefon, Frederick J., 1986-1991
    - Stocking, George W., Jr., 1976-1985
    - Stothert, Karen E., 1978, n.d.
    - Strohmier, Linda
    - Strong, John, 1993
    - Sturtevant, William C., 1960-1993, n.d.
      -See also Ser.I, Smithsonian Institution
    - Sublett, Audrey, 1965-1973
    - Sundown, Arnold, 1965-1967
    - Sundown, Corbett, 1961-1966
      - Sundown, Priscilla
    - Sundown, Priscilla, 1964
      -See also Ser.I, Sundown, Corbett
    - Swartz, Audrey
      -See Ser.I, Swartz, Marc J.
    - Swartz, Marc J., 1959-1980
      - Swartz, Audrey
    - Tait, Lyal, 1970-1971
    - Taylor, Peggy
      -See Ser.I, Russell, Eber L.
    - Taylor, Walter
    - Teeter, Karl V., 1980-1981
    - Temple University, 1964-1965
      - Gruber, Jacob W.
        -See also Ser.I, Gifford, James C.
    - Thomas, David Hurst
      -See Ser.I, Trigger, Bruce G.
    - Tippett, Alan R., 1976
    - Torok, Charles H., 1965-1968, 1976
      - Handbook of North American Indians, 1976
    - Trager, George L., 1966
    - Trigger, Bruce Graham
      - Thomas, David Hurst
        -See also Ser.I, McGill-Queens University Press
        - Folder 1, 1961-1968
        - Folder 2, 1969-1990
    - Tuck, James A., 1965-1971
      - Gifford, James C.
  - U - W (Box 6)
    - Underhill, Ruth M., 1961-1962
    - Unidentified, 1981-1988
    - United States. Department of the Interior. Bureau of Indian Affairs, 1966-1967
    - United States. National Archives, 1967
    - University of Pennsylvania. The University Museum of Archaeology and Anthropology, 1976-1988
    - Vernon, Howard A., 1976
    - Vogt, Evon Z., 1957-1970
      -See also Ser.I, Rapoport, Robert
    - Vollmann, William T., 1990, 1992
    - Von Mering, Maria, 1957-1974
    - Wagner, Sally Roesch, 1989
    - Walker, Willard, 1966-1983
    - Wallace, Anthony F.C., 1965-1979
    - Weaver, Sally M., 1966-1972
      - Abler, Thomas S.
    - White, Leslie A., 1958, 1973
    - White, Marian Emily, 1959-1976
      - Chafe, Wallace L.
    - Williams, Stephen, 1963
    - Wiren, Harold N., 1974
      -See also Ser.I, Science
    - Woodbury, Hanni, 1979-1992
    - Woodbury, Richard B., 1981
    - Woodland Indian Cultural Educational Centre, 1984
    - Wright, James V., 1964-1979
    - Wykoff, M. William, 1977, 1979
- Series II. Subject Files, 1945-1993
  Issues of Tonawanda Indian Community News from 1972 to 1973; reviews of some of Tooker's books (filed by the name of the book); programs and abstracts for meetings of the Northeastern Anthropological Association; book outlines and periodic reports about the Northeast volume of the Handbook of North American Indians; reports and meeting minutes during Tooker's membership on the Visiting Committee of the Board of Overseers of Harvard University to the Peabody Museum of Archaeology and Ethnology (1977-1981); reports (for 1961 and 1963) on the construction of the Kinzua Dam on the Allegheny River; correspondence, programs, and mailing lists for the Conference on Iroquois Research, from 1945 to 1993; and reports, meeting minutes, and notes about Iroquoia, a proposed tourist center in New York State designed to provide an historically accurate re-creation of an Iroquois community.
  - Conference on Iroquois Research #1-5 (Box 7)
    - Conference on Iroquois Research
      - Chafe, William L., 1964
      - Snow, Dean R.
      - Sturtevant, William C., 1964
        - Folder 1, 1945-1964
        - Folder 2, 1965-1968
        - Folder 3, 1969-1980
        - Folder 4, 1981-1990
        - Folder 5, 1991-1993
  - E - K (Box 8)
    - An Ethnography of the Huron Indians, 1615-1649-- Reviews, 1964, 1968, 1991
    - Fort Stanwix National Monument, 1984-1985
      -See also Ser.III, "The Iroquois Diaspora"
    - Handbook of North American Indians
      -See also Ser.I, same title
      - Folder 1, 1972-1981
      - Folder 2, 1982-1983, n.d.
    - Harvard University. Peabody Museum ofArchaeology and Ethnology
      - Folder 1, 1977-1980
      - Folder 2, 1980-1983
      - Folder 3, n.d.
    - Iroquoia
      -See also Ser.VI, Iroquoia--Dioramas
      - Folder 1, 1964-Aug. 1965
      - Folder 2, 1965 Sep.-Nov.
      - Folder 3, 1965
    - The Iroquois Ceremonial of Midwinter-- Reviews, 1970-1972
    - Iroquois Culture, History, and Prehistory-- Review, 1967
    - The Iroquois White Dog Sacrifice in the Latter Part of the Eighteenth Century-- Review, 1967
    - Kinzua Dam
      - Folder 1, 1961, 1963
      - Folder 2, 1963
  - N - U (Box 9)
    - Northeastern Anthropological Association
      - Folder 1, 1963-1969
      - Folder 2, 1969-1983, n.d.
    - Pascua-Yaqui Association, 1965
    - Tonawanda Indian Community News, 1972-1973
    - University of Pennsylvania. The University Museum of Archaeology and Anthropology, 1975-1976
- Series III. Works by Tooker, 1949-1993